you.
>> Look at your neighbor. Uh if they are
nearby, tell them you are still looking
good.
>> Better than this morning.
>> And tomorrow
>> you will continue to shine.
>> You will continue to shine.
>> In Jesus name.
>> Meta. Meta.
>> Meta.
>> Sparkle. Sparkle.
>> Sparkle sparkle.
>> Shiny shiny.
>> Shiny shiny. We can still wear shoes.
>> Amen.
>> We want to read the scriptures. It's uh
the scriptures are from the book of Mark
chapter 4. We're reading from verse 14
to 20.
This month we have entered into the sub
theme on open door declarations
and we believe that what you declare is
important.
And so we want to read this
interpretation of the parable
that Jesus spoke concerning
the swer who went out to sow seed.
So I read verse 14.
Uh let me read this in the the New King
James Version because there's something
I want uh to be highlighted there.
So it says the ser.
The swer sws the word. And these are the
ones by the wayside where the word is
sown. When they hear, Satan comes
immediately and takes away the word that
was sown in their hearts.
These likewise are the ones sown on
stony ground, who when they hear the
word immediately receive it with
gladness.
and they have no root in themselves and
so endure only for a time afterward when
tribulation or persecution arises for
the words sake immediately they stumble.
Now these are the ones sown among
thorns. They are the ones who hear the
word and the cares of this world. The
deceitfulness of riches, the desires for
other things entering in choke the word
and it becomes unfruitful.
But these are the ones sown on good
ground.
Those who hear the word accept it and
bear fruit. Psalm 30fold. Psalm 60 and
Psalm 100. This is God's word. and
gospel said
>> amen. Let's pray.
Eternal God, what a blessing that we can
come under the preaching of your word,
the teaching of your word. The Bible
says that faith comes by hearing and
hearing the word of God. Tonight, as
this word is spoken, may the Holy Spirit
take it and deposit it in good soil to
the glory of your name. Father, what a
blessing to be in God's house on this
Wednesday. Those watching us online,
Lord, we bless them that together with
us, they will receive your word in a
mighty way. We thank you for hearing our
prayer because we have prayed in Jesus'
name. And God's people said,
>> "Amen."
>> God's people said,
>> Look at your neighbor and tell your
neighbor, "The word is coming."
[clears throat]
>> Don't duck.
>> Amen. We say happy. Just allow the word
of God to minister to you. Now, this
month, we are still talking about the
year of the Lord's.
uplifted
open door and we are saying that the
door is open. You don't need to knock.
The door is open. Just go through it.
Opportunities have come. Go through
them.
And we believe that God's word is so
powerful.
But God's word on our tongue is even
more powerful.
Let me say that again.
God's word is powerful.
But God's word on our tongue is even
more powerful because it is the word
that is spoken that begins to shift and
make things happen.
The Bible says and you saw that uh in
Genesis chapter 1. If I can just go
there again, just picking up
this message of speaking the word
because this world is full of speaking,
but people are not speaking the word of
of God. They're not declaring the word
of God. And sometimes
situations and circumstances remain the
same. Not because God doesn't care, but
because nothing that God has said is
declared, is spoken. Genesis says this,
"In the beginning, God created,
the heavens and the earth, and the earth
was without form and void, and darkness
was on the face of the deep, and the
spirit of God was hovering over the face
of the waters. Then God did something to
change that environment." What did he
do? He said, he spoke. You have no idea
how powerful that is. that when we begin
to speak the vision God has given us the
whole month of January we've been
talking about vision when we begin to
declare that vision that vision begins
to get root in our situation so the
Bible says then God said
he doesn't say God thought God did what
he said what you think needs to be
spoken the Bible says out of the
abundance of the heart the mouth speaks
But interesting enough is that our
hearts are not filled with the word of
God. And so what we speak does not have
power to create because God wants us to
create. And what creates
is the word of God. And so Jesus trying
to make this lesson important and key,
he gave the parable of the swer.
And so going back to Mark 4:1, this is
what Jesus says. And he's speaking about
how the word affects our situations.
And again, he began to teach by the sea.
And a great multitude was gathered to
him. So that he got into a boat and sat
in it on the sea. And the whole
multitude was on the land facing the
sea. Then he taught them many things by
what? By parables.
and said to them in his teaching,
"Listen, behold, a swer went out to
sew." Now, they they understood this.
These guys were farmers. These guys knew
what it means to sow seed. And so, they
understood what he was saying. But he he
had a spiritual
lesson behind what he was saying. And
the Bible says in verse four, "And it
happened as he swed that some seed fell
by the wayside,
and the birds of the air came and
devoured it. Some fell on stony ground
where it did not have much earth. And
immediately it sprung up because it had
no depth of the earth.
But when the sun was up, it was
scorched, and because it had no root, it
withered away. And some seed fell among
thorns, and the thorns grew up and
choked it, and it yielded no crop.
But other seed fell on good ground, and
yielded a crop that sprung up,
increased, and produced some 30fold,
some 60, and some 100. So he's giving a
parable to begin to tell these guys the
power of the spoken word.
Tell your neighbor, "The word spoken is
powerful." The word spoken is powerful.
>> Now, I know many of you today, you've
been talking. Hello. Some of you have
been talking face to face. Others have
been talking on the phone. Others have
just been talking to yourself.
Hello. And what you say is very
powerful. And sometimes you a whole day
can be spoiled by what somebody said to
you. Whole day you woke up, it was an
exciting day. bright day, somebody said
something in number three or said
something in the office or just somebody
takes sent you a text boom your whole
day got spoiled just by a word that's
why I'm saying this the Bible says take
heed what you hear be careful what you
listen to
many times some of us immediately wake
up in the morning and we immediately we
turn on the news
We watch the news
before the news has even gone five
minutes.
Your day is spoiled.
Hello. Because let me tell you this.
Though the news is declared every day,
most of it is not good news.
Hello.
And especially when you have watched a
match and Liverpool has lost to Arsenal,
it is not good news. [laughter]
So the Bible says take heed what you
hear. There are some things you don't
want to hear just to save yourself.
But I want to tell you this, the world
will not tell you good news. The only
person who can tell you good news is
Jesus. The word of God is full of good
news. It is the word of God that says,
"Let not your hearts be troubled.
Believe in God, believe also in me."
It's the word of God that tells you that
you can do all things through Christ who
strengthen you. But but by that time
he's saying that you have just come from
an interview that you know very well you
did not make it.
But but as you are walking out, you're
saying, "I can do
>> all things through Christ who
strengthens me."
It is only God who can give you good
news. When the loan that you applied,
they come back with a news that
you did not get the loan. And
immediately God says, "My God shall
supply all your need according to his
riches in glory." It is only God's word
that can shift the balance because the
world is full of all kinds of news that
is not good news.
And so it is important for you to find
out what God is saying on a daily basis.
Let me read Psalms um chapter 1 verse
one and two and you find what he says
here in terms of the company you keep.
[clears throat]
It says this. Let me read this in the
NIV.
In the NIV, it says this.
Blessed is the one who does not. So it
starts in a negative way. First it says
blessed and then who does not. It's just
giving a contrast. So blessed is the one
who does not walk in step with the
wicked because as you're walking with
the wicked, they are talking.
Hello. So blessed is the is the one. So
go back. Blessed, blessed is the one who
does not walk in step with the wicked.
Because when you're walking with the
wicked, you're walking and you're
listening before long. Next verse
or stand. So you are walking and then
you stand to listen to more of this
story in the way that sinners take and
then afterward you do what? You sit.
Previously you are walking because you
are just passing by.
Uh and then you stand to listen to this
more. You pay more attention. And then
you pay even more attention by doing
what?
>> By sitting down. So it says, "Blessed is
the one who does not do that. Who does
not walk, stand or sit,
blessed is the one who does not do
that."
Are you getting me? But the next verse,
he says this, "But
blessed is the one who
delights, whose delight is in the law of
the Lord." Not only does he walk without
law, he stands with that law, he also
sits with that law. Whose delight is in
the law of the Lord, who meditates on
his law day and
night. This particular person go back in
the next verse uh who meditates that
person is like what? A tree planted by
streams of water there. That tree is
refreshed on a daily basis which yields
its fruit in season and whose leaf does
not wither. Whatever they do, can you
imagine that statement? Whatever they do
prospers.
The whatever means that they have
meditated on the word of God so much
that they do whatever they do according
to the word of of God. So this is what
God is saying and my message today is
titled very simply words
are seats.
Tell your neighbor, "Words are seeds."
>> Because these words fall into different
kinds of soils and they bear fruit.
Words are seeds. Take heed what you
hear, but take heed also what you say.
Be careful what you tell somebody. The
Bible says when you speak, speak words
that are seasoned so that your hearers
may be blessed. Amen. Words are seeds.
But today I want to just talk about
words and how you can take the word of
God and cause it to bear fruit for you.
So four things I'll be chasing uh
talking about these words is number one
choose the seed.
Number two release the seed. Number
three nurture the seed. Number four
harvest the seed. Now let me say it the
other way around because that word seed
is what according to Jesus is the word.
So you can say it this other way. Choose
the word,
release the word, nurture the word,
harvest the word. Hallelujah. And this
is something that we need to just learn
um and and grow in because some
sometimes the environments we live in
are so toxic because we have heard so
many negative things so much bad news
that sometimes in our brain we cannot
even look for even one word that will
encourage us. Our garden is full of
different seeds that we did not want
when I talk about choose the seeds. So
let me start there. Choose the seed.
For example,
JJ loves to eat ugali.
Hello.
And it's not just ugali. For him, he
does not just look at ugali as ugali. He
looks at the ugali as a mountain that
needs to be moved.
[laughter]
So he approaches the theali with a
strategy.
this ugali has to be moved.
Uh so when he prays he doesn't pray, oh
god bless this food before we eat it. No
he doesn't say that. He says oh god give
me the strength to move the mountain.
And before you know it the mountain is
what?
>> Is moved. But that before it reaches
there that is the harvest side.
The seed had to be what? Planted. And if
he needed the he needed to plant what
kind of seed
mace
not beans.
So first of all you check the harvest.
What harvest do you want? Then you
choose the seed because the seed will
lead to the harvest. Don't assume that
saying wicked words will produce
righteousness.
it won't happen.
Righteousness as a harvest has to be
produced by planting
righteous
seeds.
If you're going to prosper, and I'm
going to pick this up much later. If
you're going to prosper as a harvest,
what must you have planted first?
A seed of
a seed of
talk to me.
Seed of prosperity. If you're going to
harvest wisdom, you you need to have
planted what? Seeds of wisdom. If you if
you catch that statement, it will bless
your life big time. And I'll give you
some 12 seeds the Bible talks about.
So, choose the seed. Now, how do you
choose the seed? We are talking about
study the word. So, let me read Mark
4:14 one more time. Mark 4:14. Because
Jesus is now interpreting that passage
and he says, "The farmer sws the word."
A swer went out to sow seed. He sws the
word. How do you do that? You study the
word. Study the word. And as you study
the word, look for something that is
going to be a seed to your harvest.
Jesus was amazing
at being able to plant the right seeds.
But I want you to know that as you
choose the seed, you'll also need to
choose the soil
where the seed is going to go in.
Because sometimes the the seed is not
the problem. Sometimes it is what the
soil that we plant the seed. And there
are four kinds of soil that I want to
bring to your attention because um Jesus
talks about those soils. So let me read
verse 15 and then I'll come back to the
kind of seed you need to sow.
Verse 15. The Bible says some people are
like seed
along the path where the word is sown.
Remember the word is the same throughout
all that scripture. The soils are
different. There are four kinds of
soils. So some people are like seed
along the path where the word is sown.
As soon as they hear it, Satan comes and
takes away the word that was sown in
them.
What kind of soil is this? What kind of
soil is it pastor? where the word of God
is spoken and people receive it. But
before they reach the gate,
they cannot remember
what was said. It is gone. It has
disappeared.
What kind of soil is that?
So let me tell you, there are four
soils. So I'm telling you the first one,
this one is the soil of unbelief. Tell
your neighbor unbelief.
In other word, you sit listening to the
word, but you don't believe a word of
it.
Pastor, I may struggle
you anointed, but the whole time you
don't believe a thing he's saying.
For sure, by the time you reach the
gate, you will not remember anything he
said. This is what we call the word of
God is stolen.
that Satan just let me read that verse
again. Go back. Some people are like
seed along the path where the the word
is sown. As soon as they hear it, Satan
comes and takes away the word that was
sown in them. It's gone. Let me give you
an example of unbelief. Mark chapter 6.
[clears throat] Jesus is going back to
the town where he was born and
he has been doing quite a number of
miracles but when he came back to his
town
um it's like me going back to Zerico for
example you know because I was I was I
was I was raised in Islam so imagine I'm
going to lands and some of my friends uh
who we used to go to primary school with
see me and but I I come to them I'm
telling them I'm I'm the senior pastor
of Parkland's Baptist Church hello and
they said
Now people in Westlands
never saw me as they saw me as a mighty
man of God.
They have a completely different
perspective of of me. That is why for
example
your family members don't believe you.
You can come and tell them a verse that
has really encouraged you and you're
preaching to them. You're they don't
believe you.
Dad, mom, they don't believe you. Your
cousins don't believe you. Why? They
have seen you since the time when you
used to get lost while you're going to
school and you could not find your
school.
Hello. They don't believe you. It's
total unbelief. So even when you are
talking to them about faith, they're not
listening.
Now listen to this. Jesus left there and
went to his hometown accompanied by his
disciples.
When the Sabbath day came, he began to
teach in the synagogue because in
Israel, every town has a synagogue.
But then did you know that in Nairobi we
have a synagogue?
H where is it?
Just at the university there. There's a
synagogue if you if you do not know
the synagogue.
So when Jews go, they go to that
synagogue.
When the Sabbath came, he began to teach
in the synagogue. And many who heard him
were what? Amazed. Now they were amazed.
Not because they were excited. They were
just amazed.
Uh it's just like some guys when they
meet JJ and they used to live together
in Mombasa long time ago then they find
him walking pastro they wonder who JJ
JJ I don't know what you used to do in
Mombasa so I don't know why they get
surprised
[panting]
but they get shocked the same thing with
all of us
they were amazed they said where did
this man get these things. They asked,
"What's this wisdom that has been given
him?
What are these remarkable miracles he is
performing?" Then they said,
[clears throat] "Is in this the
carpenter?"
Now you see how they have lowered him.
He's a prophet. He's a man of God. They
say this guy is what? A carpenter.
Randa, he's not a prophet. Isn't this
the carpenter? Isn't this Mary's son?
They also knew him.
And the brother of James and Joseph,
Judas, and Simon. So, by the way, let me
tell you, these are the brothers of
Jesus.
So you know some of us
um we have this theology that Mary the
mother of Jesus never had other
children. So these are the ones.
Don't look at me like that. I'm saying
these are the ones because Joseph did
not marry somebody else.
Or are they cousins?
The brothers is he written there is in
this Mary's son and the brother of
James,
Joseph, Judas and Simon. Aren't his
sisters
[snorts] here with us and they did what?
>> They took offense at him. And Jesus said
to them, "A prophet
is not without honor except in his own
town, among his relatives, and in his
own home."
And then he says, "And he could not do."
Now that's a very important statement.
He could not do. Now that is different
from saying he would not do. When you
say he would not do, it means he was not
willing.
When you say he could not do is that
even though he he had the ability to do
it, he had been completely paralyzed.
He couldn't do it. He could not do any
miracles there except lay his hands on a
few sick people and heal them. He was
amazed at what?
>> The lack of faith. New King James says
it another way. that verse, that last
verse, it says it this way, if I can
read verse five. And he marveled
because of their what? Unbelief. Then he
went about the villages in Asaki
teaching and he called the 12 to himself
and began to send them out two by two.
So you can see that Jesus was paralyzed
by the people's unbelief. So that even
though you could release the word, they
were not believing it.
So that's the first soil. Okay, it is
taken away by [clears throat] the devil.
Soil number two. Let me go back to Mark.
So number two, so that I can give you
the source then go back here.
Mark 4.
All right. around verse 16 where we were
Mark chapter 4.
[clears throat]
All right. 16. Mark 4:16.
Others are like seeds sown on rocky
places. They hear the word and at once
receive it with joy.
But since they have no root, they last
only a short time. When trouble or
persecution comes because of the word,
they quickly fall away. Now, these are
the people we call the soil of
impatience. They're impatient. They want
the word of God to happen quickly. But
it's not happening.
And when [clears throat] trouble comes,
they give up on that word and it is
unfruitful. Next verse.
Still others are like seed sown among
thorns.
They hear the word but the worries of
this life the deceitfulness of wealth
and the desires for other things comes
in and choke the word making it
unfruitful. So the third soil is the
soil of anxiety or worry. People have
too many things going in their brains.
So that soil again same word no effect.
the last soil.
Others fell like others like seeds sown.
Others like seeds swn on good soil. They
hear the word, accept it, and produce a
crop. Some 30, some 60, some 100 times
what was sown. Now that soil is the soil
I believe is listening to me now.
>> Hallelujah.
It's the soil we call the soil of faith.
The Bible says, "And without faith it is
impossible to please God." It's the soil
of faith. What kind of soil is this? It
is good soil.
Uh go back to verse 20. It's good soil.
Let me read it again. Others like seed
sown on good soil. The the good soil is
that there are people who hear
the word, they accept the word, they
produce a crop 30fold, 60fold, 100fold.
Let me read that in the amplified
version just verse 20 talking about this
soil of faith.
Other seed in the in the amplified for
me please. Verse 20.
And those in the last group are the ones
on whom seed was sown on the good soil.
And they hear the word of God, the good
news regarding the way of salvation.
They accept it and bear fruit 30, 60,
and 100 times as much as was sown.
So look at your neighbor and tell your
neighbor, "My soil is not unbelief.
Tell your neighbor, "And I'm not
impatient."
>> And I'm not impatient.
>> And tell your neighbor, I don't indulge
in anxiety.
>> I don't
>> And tell your neighbor, my soil is soil
of faith.
>> My soil is soil.
>> Tell your neighbor, I have faith.
>> I have faith.
>> Uh tell your neighbor, I have a measure
of faith.
>> I have a measure of faith.
>> And so it is growing.
>> Nobody sitting here has no faith. All of
us have faith. Some of us have 10 kilos
of faith. Others have about a ton of
faith. But we all have faith.
So this is the soil. So choose the seed
that you need to sew in that soil of
faith. And that is why ladies and
gentlemen, God is saying without faith
it is impossible to please God. So
choose the seed. Study the word of God.
Find out what seed can I pick from God's
word so that I can sew it. Remember,
words are seeds. So, let me give you
some of these words that are seeds that
you can plant and then I'll I'll finish
with the rest.
There's what we call the word of wisdom.
Word of wisdom. Let me read that verse
in 1 Corinthians 12:8 talking about
spiritual gifts. But it mentions the
word of wisdom because words are seeds.
It says to one there's given through the
spirit a message of wisdom. Now let me
read this in the New King James Version.
Here it says message. It basically means
the word. For to one is given the word
of wisdom. That's a seed. And then it
goes on to say through the spirit to
another the word of knowledge. So, if
you're going to get a harvest of wisdom,
plant the word of wisdom. The seed. You
must have the seed of wisdom. And let me
tell you this,
the Bible says by wisdom a house is
built. How do you get wisdom? One of the
ways I tell people how to get wisdom
quickly is read Proverbs. Proverbs has
how many chapters?
>> 31. So that is your full month calendar.
You getting me? So what date is today?
>> Today is the 7th. So what part of
Proverbs would you read?
>> Proverbs chapter 7. As simple as that.
Now tomorrow on the 8th, if you forget
and you remember what I'm saying on the
9th.
Hello.
So you read Proverbs chapter
No, forget it. That day has gone.
>> Forget the former things.
Read Proverbs
>> nine and find out what God is saying in
Proverbs 9.
It will blow your mind what it says. So,
let me give you an example. I'm not
going to read for today. Let me read for
9th because 9th is coming. Just find
wisdom. It it sometimes it blows your
mind. Proverbs very quickly, I'm
teaching you something so that you can
catch it. It says in Proverbs 9:1,
[clears throat] "Wisdom has built her
house. She has huned out her seven
pillars." Okay, this is New King James.
Turn it into NIV. There are some people
here. Some words don't go through unless
they are NIV. Okay, here it says,
"Wisdom has built her house. She has set
up its seven pillars." So, wisdom has
seven pillars. So sometimes you look for
those pillars.
She has prepared her meat and mixed her
wine. She has also set her table.
Sometimes wisdom is spoken as if it is
feminine. Okay? So wisdom by the way in
um in in Greek wisdom is the word
Sophia.
So if your name is Sopia,
hello. That's wisdom.
Now that's where we get the word
philosophy.
Y fo Sophia.
Soph Sophia means wisdom. Filo or feel
means to love or to like. A philosopher
is a person who loves wisdom.
>> We are just teaching you English.
Okay. So
of course in Hebrew it is Hekima or
those those other things. She has set
out her servants and she calls from the
highest point of the city. Let all who
are simple come to my house. To those
who have no sense she says come eat my
food and drink the wine I have mixed. In
other words, wisdom is going to bless
you. He says leave your simple ways and
you will live. Walk in the way of
insight. Whoever corrects a mocha
invites insults. Now that is pro enough
wisdom for some of us.
Okay? Because that guy is not planning
to listen to you. Whoever corrects a
mocker
invites insults. Whoever rebukes the
wicked incurs abuse. It says, "Do not
rebuke mockers or they will do what?
Hate you. Rebuke the wise
and they will love you. Instruct the
wise and they will be wiser. still teach
the righteous and they will add to their
learning. In other words, I'm talking to
the righteous right now.
>> And you're going to add to this
learning.
>> Then he says verse 10, the fear of the
Lord is the beginning of
>> wisdom and knowledge of the holy one is
understanding.
For through wisdom your days will be
many. Now the opposite of that is what?
>> Through foolishness.
Your days will be
>> few. It says, "And the years will be
added to your life." Verse 12, "If you
are wise, your wisdom will reward you.
If you're a mocker, you alone
will suffer." Then he says, "Folly is an
unruly woman."
Can we continue?
Folly is an unruly woman. She is simple
and knows nothing. Ah that's bad.
Remember we are comparing wisdom and
foolishness.
So she sits at the door of her house on
a seat at the highest point of the city.
Now remember he's just describing a
woman as describing the first woman who
was wise. Wisdom is a woman who is wise.
But also there's a woman who is foolish.
Hello. These are just metaphors. Tell
your neighbor metaphors.
>> So I'll not finish this. This is for you
to finish. [panting]
But let me tell you this. I have really
loved proverbs because I'm telling you
every day I would read Proverbs. I would
get so wise. So plant those words. You
will reap a lot of harvest. Another one
is the word of of knowledge which I will
not repeat. Then the word of peace. Uh
words of peace. Then words of words in a
season. Let me read Proverbs 15:23
I believe
um Proverbs 15:23.
A person
finds joy in giving an apt reply and how
good is a timely word. Now let me read
this in the New King James because it
talks about season.
A man has joy by the answer of his
mouth. And a [clears throat] word spoken
in due season, how good it is. In other
words, there are words that when they
spoken in the right season, they bring a
lot of joy. And we can I can give you
even more words uh about the kind of
words you should speak. Let me read one
more. Zechariah 11:17 talks about the
word of prosperity.
And he says this, Zechariah 11:17.
Zachchariah.
Ah yeah, we're getting there. Zechariah
is in the Old Testament.
Ah yeah. It says again proclaim saying,
"Thus says the Lord of hosts, my cities
shall again spread out through what?
>> Prosperity." Your cities will will
prosper. I'm saying when you release
this word, your city will spread out
through prosperity. So decree those
words. So let me stop there about the
words. But I was saying all this to say
this. Choose
the seed.
Choose the seed. You want to be healed.
There's a seed for that. Let me read
Jeremiah 33:6
about healing. because I pray that many
of you will be healed. Those people in
the hospital will be healed. Um, you'll
have health. Listen to this, this verse.
Behold, I will bring it health and
healing. I will heal them and reveal to
them the abundance of peace and truth.
Behold, I will bring it health. God
wants you healed.
>> I'm saying God wants you healed. The
Bible says he sent forth his word and
did what?
>> And healed them. May God's word heal
you.
>> So choose your harvest by planting the
right seed. So study the word. Number
two, release the word. So these ones,
I'll just go very fast through them.
Release the word. Okay. So a seed.
Pastor Ashira, by the way, Pastor Shira
is a pastor, but he's also a farmer.
Hello.
just just observe him.
Just farmers uh you know farmers uh
farmers. So he's a farmer and sometimes
he plants things and they don't grow
[laughter]
but release the seed. Mark 4:3 says
this.
Listen, a farmer went out to do what? To
sow seed. In other words,
[clears throat]
if you walk with seeds in your pocket,
when will you have a harvest?
When
>> you never have a harvest.
Seeds must be pulled out of your pocket.
Find the soil. Plant it. Now remember,
the soil we're talking about is what?
>> The soil of the soil of
>> faith. Take a word of God, believe it,
put it in faith. It will grow for you.
I'm saying it will grow for you.
>> There's somebody sitting here. You've
been trying to finish your degree and
because of a number of things uh it's
just told. That journey is told. Let me
tell you this. Begin to plant the word
that says you will graduate.
>> Amen.
>> Go somewhere. Get a marker and get a
piece of paper and get a black marker or
a blue marker or even a red marker and
and write there I will graduate
>> with a bachelor's whatever of science or
I will graduate or with my masters. That
is a seed you're planting right now.
There is no idea how you're going to
graduate.
Number one, you don't have the school
fees. You're busy. You're a family man
trying to sort out your family issues.
You're doing your master's family issues
became many. You stopped. But let me
tell you this in Jesus name.
You will graduate.
>> I'm saying you will graduate.
>> That's a seed you're planting. You're
releasing it into the soil of faith and
saying, "God, you're the alpha and the
omega. What you begin, you finish. And
God, what you began in me, I will do
what? I'll finish." Somebody better
receive that.
So plant that seed every if it is still
in your brain and you don't say it
nothing will happen. The Bible says you
know write the vision down so that those
who read it may run with it. Uh the
vision may tar but it will happen in
Jesus name. It will happen in Jesus
name. Hello.
There's a lady in our church here, but
she goes to another church now.
She she she she wanted to get married.
Yeah. She wanted to get married.
She was 30. She was not married.
Hello.
35.
She's not married.
One day she came to my office. She says,
"Ambro,
pray for me because when I leave your
office, I know I will be married."
Now that now she was serious. She really
wanted to get married but the horizon of
marriage was not there.
Hello.
So
because I knew her for a long time you
know even for me as a pastor I'm
wondering m
the way things are going here
nothing will happen you know because
sometimes we also have our own doubts
say nothing is going to happen here but
because she took it very seriously that
if Ambrose if pas Ambrose prays for her
she has faith that God will hear
And so we prayed. I said in Jesus name.
Now I'm praying for her because it is
her who needs to be married, not me. So
I'm praying
[panting] for her to receive the
miracle. And so I prayed and released it
because you release that prayer and that
faith and that word into faith allow God
to work it out.
Amazingly,
this lady meets a man and I had told her
where the day you meet that guy, bring
him to me
because there are some guys who waste
your time. But you bring them to me, I
will discern.
[panting]
I have a machine to discern. I'll just
say no.
No, I have no machine. I just want
somebody who is courageous enough to
come and see Pastor Ambrose
will think twice. And so if they you
tell I want you to go see Pastor
Ambrose. You say uh uh I'm not going to
see that man of God, then for sure that
is not the guy you should marry.
I'm just giving you advice.
Hallelujah.
>> Anyway, he met this guy and guess what?
He brought the guy to my office.
The guy was not from Kenyaga.
He was not from Kisum.
He was not from coast.
The guy was from the United Kingdom.
Hallelujah.
[panting]
So, you know, she was looking for a
person to find her. That guy was very
far. So God had to bring him to Kenya.
This guy was busy in Kenya. So anyway,
long story short, they met
and the lady said, "I'm taking you to
Pastor Ambrose." They he brought the guy
to me. We sat, I talked to him, you
know, had a good conversation. We
finished, you know, and I I in my spirit
I said the this this guy can make a good
husband.
Long story short, I married the two
I married the two
and they continued their life.
This girl
got pregnant. They tried her to be
pregnant. She's over 40, 45.
They tried this, they tried that, all
kinds of things, but they're praying.
A year ago, a year and a half ago, she
got pregnant.
triplets
to sweet too nice to chubby triplets.
You know, when when we got that story
and and Martha Martha Martha was I
believe Martha was her best ma mate.
Looking at those kids, my mind went back
to that time she came to my office and
said, "Ambroth,
I need to get married. A seed was
planted."
Fast forward,
she has a family triplets.
What a blessing.
But the seed needed to be planted. The
moment it was still in her head, in her
mind, it would stay there until she goes
to heaven.
Let me tell you this, the word of God
does not go and come back
>> void. It will accomplish what God sends
it to do. I just used the illustration
of marriage as an example, but you can
use it in terms of your career, your
work, your education, your children.
Plant seeds now, you will harvest
tomorrow.
Hallelujah. Every day, plant seeds of
selfworth. Look at yourself in the
mirror and say, "I'm looking at the most
handsome person in in in the world." And
and and that person is me.
Because there are people who planted the
wrong seeds in your life. They told you
you'll never make up to anything. You're
the most ugliest thing they have ever
seen.
And they planted that seed and you
believed it. And that thing is torturing
you every day. Even though you are so
beautiful, every time you look at the
mirror, you're not seeing who God
created you. You are listening to the
word that was spoken to you. That word
mirrors you every day. And today, I'm
here to approve that word. Now, I say
you're the most beautiful person in this
world. You're the best. You're the best.
Oh, I'm telling you, you're the best.
Uh, believe that. Change your mindset.
The wrong seed was planted. We approve
it in Jesus name.
>> You were not created for poverty. Now
I'm telling you,
>> you're going to die a millionaire
>> and you're going to live to enjoy it in
Jesus name. Uh I'm planting that seed in
your life. And through the journey, you
may stumble and fall. You may go
bankrupt, you know, and all kinds of
things. You may even be deceived by
people who come in Westlands and tell
you, can I read your palm?
How can I read your palm? My friend,
never give anybody your palm to read. I
see I see
I see millions. I see a young man with a
red shirt coming your way.
Before you know it, they can take your
money
and they'll be gone. Especially those
guys who try to multiply your money.
If you were,
>> you'll be rich anyway. Amen.
>> Not through people reading your palm.
>> Plant the right seed
>> and it will germinate. It will grow. It
will prosper
without you getting into many problems
in life.
>> The reason why I keep talking about
passports is I keep planting seeds.
Those are seeds. Uh on Sunday, another
guy came to me says, "Pastor Ambrose,
imagine next Sunday I'll not be here.
I'm on my way to Canada.
Yeah, you better give God a big hand.
I'm on my way to Canada because we we
plant these seeds. We say you the
borders are open for you. Yes, obstacles
are there. Challenges are there. All
kinds of things. But guess what? You're
going to the US. You're going to
Australia. You're going to France. Even
though you don't know how to speak
French, you're going there anyway.
Another
guy one time said, "Ambro, pray for me.
I I I'm a chef and my desires one day to
work on a cruise ship."
I looked at the guy, I said, "He has no
structure
to ever be on a cruise ship. Cruise
ships are very expensive." This guy
said, "But me, I like cooking, but I
want to be cooking on a cruise ship."
Prayed. He got a passport.
God opened a door for him. Amazingly
last year around I think it was around
December. He had come home and he said,
"Pastor, I'm back. I've traveled more
than 10 countries
on a cruise ship and I'm just here on
holiday because I'm going back." His
passport has been filled so many times.
And I said this Jama who was just
looking kawa
tell your neighbor even though I'm
looking kawa even though I'm looking
there's an there's extraordinary in me
>> don't don't take for me
I'm planting a seed in your life
I'm planting a seed in your somebody's
life right now I'm talking about
greatness. There's greatness that is
coming your way now
>> in Jesus name.
>> Yes, there's greatness coming your way.
I believe that. I believe that. I
believe that.
Oh, but Ambrose, you know, I don't have
capital, my friend. You have capital.
His name is Jesus Christ.
>> His name is Jesus Christ.
His name is Jesus Christ. You have
capital. Trust that capital. Oh, Ambros,
I don't have a bank account. Yeah, you
have one. Jesus is your bank account.
>> Just shift your mind in Jesus name.
Let me finish this because I said choose
your seed and then do what? Release your
seed by planting it. I have two more and
I'll say them in succession. Three is
nurture the seed. In other words,
believe that that seed will grow. Let me
read Mark 11:20 very quickly. Uh 20 and
to 23. Believe. So don't just plant it,
but believe that what you have done, God
is going to do something. All right.
Okay. Can I get Mark? My screen there is
off. In the morning, as they went along,
they saw the fig tree withered from the
roots. Peter remembered and said to
Jesus, "Rabbi, look, the fig tree you
cast has withered."
Then Jesus said, "Have
faith in God." Jesus answered. And then
he said, "Truly I tell you, if anyone
says to this mountain, go throw yourself
into the sea and does not
doubt in their heart, but does what?
>> Believes. Believes. Believes." That's
how you nurture your seed. Just believe.
Believe that the God who gave it to you
will make it happen.
>> Just believe. Uhhuh. Believe and keep
believing. Uh, doesn't take much. Just
believe.
By the way, Pastor Shira, what's the
difference between believing in God and
believing God?
Now, of course, since you're from Yerry,
you may be having a very difficult time
to give me the an answer, but I'm asking
all of us, what's the difference between
believe in God and believe God?
Let me say it this way.
What's the difference in believing in
Ambrose and believing Ambrose?
H.
Somebody needs a mic. Huh? But anyway,
let me let me let me let me help you.
Believing in somebody is believing in
the totality of who that person is.
Believing them is believing something
they said
because what they said represents them.
So God is saying believe me.
Believe my word
because behind that word is the King of
Kings
and the Lord of Lords. Amen.
Believe. So tell your neighbor, nurture
the seed,
>> nurture the seed
>> by believing.
>> Don't doubt.
>> Now from time to time you may doubt
because either the thing is waiting for
so long is not happening quickly and
sometimes circumstances just shift but
keep believing
for he who declared it will surely bring
it to pass.
Remember the verse that I keep repeating
to you that God will not postpone that
which he has said and especially this
year there are things God is not going
to postpone
>> concerning you.
>> Let me read just for the sake of
somebody here and then we'll finish.
Ezekiel 12 26. So this is just to
encourage somebody to believe the word
of God. It says this, the word of the
Lord came to me. Therefore say to them,
this is what the sovereign Lord says.
None of my words will be delayed any
longer. Whatever I say will be
fulfilled, declares the sovereign Lord.
In the New King James, it says this same
verses 26-28.
It says again the word of the Lord came
to me saying son of man look the house
of Israel is saying the vision that he
sees is for many days from now and he
prophesies of times far off. Therefore
say to them thus says the Lord God none
of my words will be postponed any more.
Believe God.
But the word which I speak
will be done
>> says the Lord
>> your God. Believe him.
Finally, as you stand on your feet,
let me finish with the number four.
Remember I said from beginning words are
what?
Words are
>> seats. So what is number one?
Choose.
Choose
>> the seed. Number two,
>> release the seed. In other words,
declare the word. Number three,
>> nurture the seed. In other words,
believe the word. And the last one,
>> harvest the seed. Now, how do you
harvest the seed? By simply
receiving God's word with expectation.
This is what the Bible says in Mark
4:20. There must be an expectation. It
says this. Other seeds others like seeds
sown on good soil hear the word, accept
it, and produce a crop. Some 30, some
60, some 100 times what was sown.
There's a harvest.
Abraham waited for the harvest. This is
what the Bible says in Romans chapter 4
verse 20.
He received the word with expectation.
He did not waver at the promise of God
through what? and belief, but was
strengthened in faith, giving glory to
God, and being fully convinced that what
he had promised, he was also able to
perform. And therefore, it was accounted
to him for righteousness.
Expect God's word. It will be fulfilled.
>> Receive it even when you don't see it.
The Bible says in Mark 11 verse
24 concerning praying because sometimes
prayers are also words. Therefore I say
to you whatever things you ask uh let me
say that again. Therefore I tell you
whatever you ask for in prayer believe
that you
>> you that you
the word have is important. Believe you
>> have received it and it will be
>> yours. You will reach your destination.
>> You will reach your destination.
Amen. You will reach your destination.
There's a lady
uh and I was just listening this. It was
on on YouTube. I was listening to her
testimony and she she did all these
things that I'm saying. Um she went to a
church, she started listening to the
word of God, believing God's word, and
then one day she her faith rose and she
prayed a prayer. She said, "Oh God,"
this is the US said, "Oh God, one of my
desire," because she's a um um an
interior designer.
And she said, "God,
I know I'm going to ask you something
right now. I don't really believe with
my mind it can happen, but I'm going to
ask anyway." and she said, "God, give me
an opportunity to decorate at the White
House."
That's what she's an interior designer.
She said, "I want to decorate
something at the White House."
So, what she did the following day is
that she wrote a letter. During that
time, Trump was a president. She wrote a
letter to white house and she just sent
it and she believed that out of she was
not known. She was just an average
woman. But look at yourself and tell
yourself I am more than average. I'm
extraordinary. Tell your neighbor.
>> Tell your neighbor I may look average
>> but inside me
>> there's extraordinariness.
>> Hallelujah.
Long story short, one day she receives a
note. She was just passing. She looked
at the computer and she saw a letter
from the White House.
She checked. She was one of the people
who had been shortlisted.
70 out of 70. She was one of the people
who was going to the White House during
Christmas when they celebrate Christmas.
Uh the White House celebrates Christmas
and she was going to decorate one of the
decorators.
She went to the White House. She was one
of the decorators. Some of people were
doing walls, others were doing flowers.
But she spent there nearly two weeks at
the White House decorating.
Her harvest had come.
Something that looks totally impossible,
God is able to make it possible.
>> What is your harvest? Where do you want
to go? Plant the seed today. And some of
it may germinate so fast because this is
the year of what?
>> Acceleration. Some of you are going to
get a tender that will blow your mind.
>> It will blow your mind.
>> Just send it. Send us. You may not even
have the ability to actually fulfill
that tender.
Hello.
But who knows a God who can organize
resources
and channel it just to you
>> and for you to make it happen. I'm
telling you
the God we serve is an awesome God.
>> Remember
God wants us to go to heaven but before
we reach there
God wants heaven to come on earth.
>> Look at your neighbor tell their
neighbor thy kingdom come. th
>> thy will be done on earth.
>> Thy will be done on earth
>> as it is in heaven.
>> In Jesus name.
>> in Jesus name.
>> And by the way, just again as a as a as
wisdom,
don't share your big dreams with
smallminded people.
If you want that dream to be shot down,
share it with small-minded people. Look
for big-minded people
and they will cause your dream to become
bigger.
And one of those big-minded people is
standing in front of you.
God has enlarged me in my mind. But
there are many of them. Pastor Ash is
one of them. Uh Rapo by the way.
Rapando. Uh Rapo the one who was praying
here.
Uh come come up here. This this Jama who
looks very average.
Uh
uh and some of you think because he's
skinny he has a skinny spirit in him.
No,
this guy is a very serious architect.
>> Just give him your ideas, he will put
them on paper.
He's an amazing architect.
Sometimes you don't know the people you
are interacting with. God has put
extraordinary things in them.
This guy,
not only can he draw for you,
leave it to him. He can bring that
drawing into reality
from beginning to finish.
This guy, Deacon Rapo,
Deacon Rapo,
Pastor Ash here used to work for Safar.
Those big masks you see for Safharico,
he was a guy who was dealing with them.
Somebody say, "Oh,
somebody saying aha,
amazing people."
And Kendra Po, we celebrate you. We
celebrate the work you do. May God open
doors for you this year in Jesus name.
Jesus name.
So we celebrate the gifts that are here.
I'm not an architect but I can depend on
architects to make things happen.
Our children's facility where the junior
school is.
If you have ever been there
he was one of the architects.
Yes. The GSS building.
amazing things.
So I may be standing here and Kumbbe
next to you is a a project financial.
So look at your neighbor and tell your
neighbor I know you are extraordinary.
>> God is good.
>> Are you ready for me to bless you?
>> Yes.
>> I have released seeds in your life.
Amen.
>> I've chosen them. I've released them.
May you nurture them by believing them
and you will surely have a harvest.
>> The amazing thing about the harvest,
Pastor Shira, is that if you plant one
seed of maze with the day you harvest,
it's on it's on one stock and there are
two maze comps. If you count the seeds
here that came out of one seed, it will
blow your mind. That's the miracle of a
seed.
Plant your seed. Amen.
>> Plant your words. But my prayer is this.
Please, if the if good seeds can grow,
bad seeds
can also grow.
So, choose your seed. One word can
destroy a whole nation, but one word can
lift a whole nation. Choose your words.
Amen.
>> So, I'm declar I'm declaring you
victorious.
>> Amen.
>> Starting tonight. Amen.
>> Yes. I'm speaking to your business and
I'm saying your business will flourish
>> in Jesus name. You are being expanded.
You're being enlarged.
>> There is goodness in you.
>> Ah people thought you're wicked but
there is goodness in you.
>> Jesus is in you.
>> People thought that in your head there's
nothing but water.
Amen.
Amazing ideas. But remember this,
seed time and harvest shall remain. Seed
time and harvest. Between seed and
harvest
time.
Some of us give up. We just think seed
harvest. But between seed and harvest,
there's time. For some of us, it is just
one week. For others, it's about a
month. For others, it is a year, but it
shall come to pass. It shall come to
pass. Amen.
So give your neighbor a high five and
tell them thanks for coming today
>> in Jesus name.
Yes,
I told you you'd look better than when
you came and you are surely shining in
Jesus name.
>> Amen.
>> Let us pray. Father, as we stand, we are
just celebrating your love for us. And
dear Lord, this teaching is a teaching
that is setting us up for this month.
help us to receive this word because
words are seeds. I'm praying for
somebody online
and they are be they're beginning to get
excited about some of the things I've
just said. And they're saying, "I
receive it. I receive it, Pastor
Ambrose. I receive it." And I'm saying,
"My brother, my sister, choose your
seed. Release your seed. Nurture that
seed. The harvest will surely come." God
is not a man that he should lie. He's
not a son of man that he should change
his mind. Has he said it and will he not
do it? Has he spoken it and will he not
fulfill it? Oh God, just like I said
earlier, your word is powerful, but your
word in on our tongue is even more
powerful. May we speak that word.
Father, thank you for tonight. May this
word continue to
bring a great harvest because it has
already been released. May we nurture it
through our faith. May we get a harvest,
Lord. May we plant in the good soil, the
soil of faith. Lord, let us may we run
away from unbelief,
from impatience,
and from worry and anxiety. May we plant
this seed in faith and it shall surely
bring a harvest 30fold, 60fold, and
100fold. If you believe that, you better
say, I receive it.
>> I receive it.
>> I take it.
>> It is my portion.
>> And there's nothing the devil can do
about it.
>> There's nothing.
>> And God's people said,
>> "Amen."
>> Come on.
Amen.
As I prepare to bless us, this card we
gave to this this worship um on
Wednesday. Many of you got this card um
and it was just written so that you
could have seats to speak. But we have
now put it uh into
uh a pack and uh in this pack it is
called Open Door Park. Not only do you
have this card, you also have another
card which some of you may have seen it
earlier. It is called you are card.
These are seeds for you to speak to
yourself. And for example, you are
simply says you are a winner.
>> So I'm saying it to you. You are a
winner.
>> Amen.
>> You are loved.
>> You are special.
>> Amen.
>> You have what it takes.
>> You have amazing opportunities coming
your way.
>> Amen. You are more than a conqueror.
>> Amen.
>> You are positioned for promotion.
>> You're bigger than you think.
>> Amen.
>> You are a success.
>> You are royalty and circumstances bow
before you.
>> Amen.
>> You're destined for greatness.
>> You're God's good news on earth.
>> Amen.
>> I'm saying you're God's good news on
earth.
>> Amen.
>> You are celebrated.
>> In other words, you're a celeb.
>> You are forgiven.
>> Amen.
>> You are favored.
>> You are attractive. Amen.
>> You are approved.
>> Amen.
>> You are light.
>> You are rising.
>> Amen.
>> You are undefeated.
>> You are peaceful.
>> Amen.
>> You are healthy.
>> You are strong.
>> Amen.
>> You are fashioned in the image of God,
your creator.
>> Amen.
>> Believe it.
>> Receive it.
>> Possess it.
>> It is your portion.
>> It is portion.
>> It is God-given.
>> Arise and shine.
>> Amen.
I hope you can get this. This card is in
in the in the bookshop. It is in this
pack. Uh plus the other card I showed
you. You can get a copy of it. Uh get a
pack, share it with your friends, and
just have some seeds to plant.
Amen.
>> I hope the bookshop is open,
but they're here. Okay. So, get a park.
It will bless you. While we taking tea,
by the way, tell your neighbor there's a
cup of tea.
>> Amen.
>> Tell your neighbor it is for you.
>> Tell your neighbor, take the tea, but
don't take the cup away.
>> Are you glad you came
>> Amen. Look at your neighbor. Tell your
neighbor, surely goodness
>> surely goodness
>> and mercy
>> shall follow you
>> all the days of your life
>> all the days of your life.
>> And you shall dwell in the house of the
Lord. He shall live
>> forever,
>> forever
>> and ever
>> and ever.
>> And there's nothing the devil can do
about it.
>> And now, may the grace of our Lord Jesus
Christ and the love of God and the
fellowship of the Holy Spirit be with us
now and forever more. Amen. Have a good
night.